Guide to the Nathaniel T. Allen Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nathaniel T. Allen collection
1834-2009
1843-1903
GEN MSS 1401
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.54
5 boxes + 1 broadside
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers of educator and social reformer Nathaniel T. Allen, and biographical and research materials about him. Manuscripts in each series are accompanied by additional photocopied materials, some annotated by an unidentified researcher; for most, locations of originals are unidentified.
Allen, Nathaniel T. (Nathaniel Topliff), 1823-1903
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1846-1902. II., Notebooks, 1843-1871. III. Other Writings, 1869-1902. IV. Biographical Materials, 1834-1993. V. Other Papers, 1840s-2009.
Biographical / Historical
Nathaniel T. (Nathaniel Topliff) Allen (1823-1903) was an American educator and social reformer. Allen graduated from the State Normal School (Bridgewater, Mass.) in 1845, and attended the Rensselaer Institute (later Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute) in 1847. During 1848-1853, he was principal of the Model School in West Newton, Massachusetts, which was associated with the State Normal School at West Newton (later Framingham State University), founded by Horace Mann, Secretary of the Massachusetts State Board of Education. Allen founded the West Newton English and Classical School in 1854, and served as its director until 1900. Teachers at the West Newton English and Classical School included Allen's wife, Caroline Swift Bassett Allen (1830-1915); his brothers George Ellis Allen (1817-1888), Joseph Addison Allen (1819-1904), and James Theodore Allen (1831-1900); and his daughters, Fanny Bassett Allen (1857-1913) and Lucy Ellis Allen (1867-1943), who also founded the Misses Allen School in West Newton in 1904. Nathaniel T. Allen was an advocate of social reforms including abolition and women's suffrage, and his educational reforms and innovations included kindergarten, co-education of boys and girls, racial integration, and study of natural science and physical fitness.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from M & S Rare Books on the Jockey Hollow Fund, 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers of educator and social reformer Nathaniel T. Allen, and biographical and research materials about him. Manuscripts in each series are accompanied by additional photocopied materials, some annotated by an unidentified researcher; for most, locations of originals are unidentified.
Correspondence with family, colleagues, and students, 1846-1902, includes letters from Allen to his family, 1851, about travel from Charleston, South Carolina, to New Orleans, Louisiana, with observations on slavery and other impressions of the South; letters to Allen from colleagues, 1865, about his acquittal on charges of assaulting and causing the death of a student; and condolence letters following the death of his daughter, Sarah Caroline Allen Cooney (1861-1897).
Notebooks include student notes from the State Normal School (Bridgewater, Mass.), 1845-1846, about arithmetic, algebra, geometry, physiology, geography, and grammar, and the Rensselaer Institute, 1847, about botany and chemistry; teaching notes relating to the Model School in West Newton, 1852-1853; notes, accounts, and a scrapbook from travel in Europe and research on education in Germany, 1869-1871; and catalogs of his library and mineral specimens, undated. Other writings include a draft biography of Irish social reformer and suffragist Frances Power Cobbe, undated; and notes, articles, and speeches, 1869-1902 and undated, relating to education, politics, religion, travel, and other subjects.
Biographical materials include memoirs by Allen, 1884 and undated; biographical sketches from published reference sources, 1890-1929; a typescript eulogy by Julian Clifford Jaynes, minister of the First Unitarian Society in West Newton; obituaries; and other articles about Allen and the West Newton English and Classical School, 1853-1993.
Other papers include real estate deeds and maps for properties owned by Allen and his family in West Newton and Medfield, Massachusetts, 1840s-1911; financial accounts with James Theodore Allen, Joseph Addison Allen, and others, 1843-1893; a photograph of a school picnic, 1892, and reproductions of photographs of Allen, 1840s and undated; printed material including advertisements for Pinehurst Resort, North Carolina, 1897-1898 and undated; and a small amount of notes and research material by an unidentified researcher, 2009 and undated.
Education -- Massachusetts; Education -- Germany; Educators -- Massachusetts; Abolitionists -- Massachusetts; Coeducation -- Massachusetts; School integration -- Massachusetts; Slavery -- Southern States; Slavery -- United States; Women -- Suffrage -- United States; Medfield (Mass.: Town) -- Maps; Medfield (Mass.: Town) -- Social life and customs; Pinehurst (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Southern States -- Description and travel; West Newton (Newton, Mass.) -- Social life and customs; Photographs; Abolitionists -- Massachusetts -- 19th century; Educators -- Massachusetts -- 19th century; Allen, Caroline Swift Bassett, 1830-1915; Allen, Fanny Bassett; Allen, George Ellis, 1817-1888; Allen, James Theodore, 1831-1900; Allen, Joseph Addison, 1819-1904; Allen, Lucy, 1793-1889; Allen, Lucy Ellis; Allen, Nathaniel T. (Nathaniel Topliff), 1823-1903; Cobbe, Frances Power, 1822-1904; Cooney, Sarah Allen; Jaynes, Julian Clifford, 1854-1922; Pinehurst Resort & Country Club (Pinehurst, N.C.); Rensselaer Institute -- Students; State Normal School at Framingham, Mass; State Normal School at West Newton (Mass.); State Normal School (Bridgewater, Mass.) -- Students; West Newton English and Classical School
- Correspondence, 1846-1902; Series I; 0.21; 1 box
  - Correspondence, 1846-1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865 February-June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notebooks, 1843-1871, undated; Series II; 0.42; 1 box
  - Autograph collection, 1843-1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - State Normal School (Bridgewater, Mass.), 1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State Normal School (Bridgewater, Mass.), 1846 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rensselaer Institute (botany), 1847 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rensselaer Institute (chemistry), 1847 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - State Normal School at West Newton (Mass.), 1852-1853 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Travel in Europe, 1869-1871 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Travel in Europe (materials formerly laid in), 1864-1870 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Travel in Europe scrapbook, 1869-1871 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Library catalog, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mineral specimens catalog, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Other Writings, 1869-1902, undated; Series III; 0.21; part of 1 box
  - Education, 1902, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Education in Germany, 1869-1872, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Francis Power Cobbe, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Other subjects, 1888-1901 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Other subjects, undated (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Newspaper articles and letters to editors, 1874-1901, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Biographical Materials, 1834-1993, undated; Series IV; 0.21; part of 1 box
  - Memberships, 1834-1903 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Memoir, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Memoir, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Memoir by Lucy Allen (excerpts), 1885 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Other memoirs (excerpts), 1844-1901, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Published biographical sketches, 1890-1929 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Eulogy by Julian Clifford Jaynes, [1903] (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Obituaries, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Articles about Allen and the West Newton English and Classical School, 1853-1993 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
- Other Papers, 1840s-2009; Series V; 0.21; part of 1 box
  - Financial accounts with James Theodore Allen, 1875-1901, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Financial accounts with Joseph Addison Allen, 1886-1898 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Other financial accounts, 1843-1893 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Photographs, 1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Printed material: Pellew, George, Woman and the Commonwealth, or, A Question of Expediency (Boston: Houghton, Mifflin and Company, 1892) (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Printed material about Maine, 1893-1898, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Printed material about Pinehurst Resort, North Carolina, 1897-1898, undated (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Other printed material, 1871-1896, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Real estate deeds, 1840s-1911, undated (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - Real estate maps
  - Real estate papers about Allen's house in Medfield, Massachusetts, 1876-1878 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Notes by an unidentified researcher, 2009, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Oversize Materials
  - Newspapers articles and letters to editors (Series III), 1900, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Memberships (Series IV), 1865 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Printed material about Pinehurst Resort, North Carolina (Series V), 1898 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Other printed material (Series V), 1891, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Real estate maps (Series V), 1902, 1910 (Box 6 (Broadside))